Welcome back to A Push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. It's time to talk about the
official African-American Civil Rights
Movement. We already talked about the
roots of this with Rosa Parks, the bus
boycott, and the Little Rock Nine, but
pretty quickly the movement expands even
bigger. So, here is what you need to
know. During the early part of the Civil
Rights Movement in the '60s, the overall
goal was non-violent protest because
violence would undermine the goal of the
movement. The leader of this movement
will be a man named Martin Luther King
Jr. So, why don't we go through some
examples of this movement? Sit-ins were
protests where black activists sat at
segregated lunch counters refusing to
leave until served. Freedom rides
happened where people of many races sat
in white-only sections of buses
throughout the South to challenge
segregation. And finally, there were a
lot of marches in big cities. For
example, in the March on Washington,
Martin Luther King Jr. went up on a
stage and gave his I Have a Dream speech
where he pleaded [music] to thousands of
people about his dreams of a world
without blatant segregation. And it
would easily become one of the most
famous speeches in world history. And by
this point, the non-violent movement had
gotten so big that it finally pushed
real federal action. The 1964 Civil
Rights Act is passed, which completely
ends segregation and bans
discrimination. The Voting Rights Act is
also passed, which protected black
voting rights. And also, the other two
branches of government do a few things
as well. Here is the issue though,
because even if the federal government
passed all these laws, poverty still
exists, racism still exists, and urban
violence actually steadily rises. And
this is where the Civil Rights Movement
will essentially split in half. On one
side, you have the Martin Luther King
inspired non-violent protest, but now on
the other side, you have a growing group
of people advocating for more aggressive
measures like self-defense, black pride,
and economic independence. A leader to
reference here is Malcolm X. This second
movement based on black power gets
really popular and leads to groups like
the Black Panthers who again advocate
for more aggressive measures. It's also
important to note that these two very
important leaders will get assassinated,
which definitely does not help the
non-violent side of things. So, there is
an obvious split here, and this will
mean by the midpoint of the '60s, the
civil rights movement is not necessarily
one thing anymore. It is a movement
divided behind different methods, full
of a lot of ongoing struggles. On the
screen now are AP style questions for
this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.